<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>CDK on tech-lessons.in</title>
    <link>//localhost:1313/en/tags/cdk/</link>
    <description>Recent content in CDK on tech-lessons.in</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="//localhost:1313/en/tags/cdk/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Concluding Serverless Journey</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/en/blog/concluding_serverless_journey/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/en/blog/concluding_serverless_journey/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We have come a long way in our &lt;a href=&#34;//localhost:1313/en/blog/beginning_serverless_journey&#34;&gt;Serverless journey&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;. This journey which started with building a serverless application has finally come to a stage where we can see all&#xA;our hard work in action. We will be deploying our application in this article.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We will be using &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.aws.amazon.com/cdk/latest/guide/home.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;AWS CDK&lt;/a&gt;&#xA; to deploy our application. Before we start using CDK, let&amp;rsquo;s quickly look at what is CDK -&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The AWS Cloud Development Kit (AWS CDK) is an open source software development framework to model and provision your cloud application resources using familiar programming languages.&#xA;Provisioning cloud applications can be a challenging process that requires you to perform manual actions, write custom scripts, maintain templates, or learn domain-specific languages.&#xA;AWS CDK uses the familiarity and expressive power of programming languages for modeling your applications. It provides you with high-level components that preconfigure cloud resources with&#xA;proven defaults, so you can build cloud applications without needing to be an expert. AWS CDK provisions your resources in a safe, repeatable manner through AWS CloudFormation&lt;/strong&gt;.&#xA;It also enables you to compose and share your own custom components that incorporate your organization&amp;rsquo;s requirements, helping you start new projects faster.&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://aws.amazon.com/cdk/&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://aws.amazon.com/cdk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://aws.amazon.com/cdk/&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
